Imagine someone sitting there eating
yogurt, telling everyone around them
that the probiotics in their yogurt are
a musthave for any healthy diet. People
have lost interest in the discussion
long ago, but they keep hammering on how
wonderful probiotics are if you want
good gut health. And people are
desperately trying to change the
subject. They've even started talking
about the weather because they're tired
of talking about yogurt. Now, imagine
it. But you've had enough. You snap and
you blurt out, "Probiotics aren't that
great. They can actually be really
harmful to the stunned silence of
everyone at the table." Then the yogurt
evangelist replies, "That's crazy. My
yoga podcast had a nutritionist on that
said, "Probiotic yogurt is incredible
for you." And then you say, "Then watch
this video, you yogurt fiend." And then
what if I told you that probiotics are
linked to worse cancer outcomes? And
what if I told you another gut health
product is linked to improved cancer
outcomes? Well, don't take my word for
it. Like a yoga podcast with some random
nutritionist. Let's look at the study on
that very topic. In this study,
researchers recruited latestage cancer
patients and most of which were being
treated using an amunotherapy called an
antiPD1 therapy. In short, it's an
antibbody that binds to a protein called
PD1 on immune cells that target cancer
cells. When bound, they block an
inhibitory protein called PDL protein
from interacting with it. When blocked
by this antibbody, the immune cell
remains active and continues to attack
cancer cells. So, antiPD1 therapy keeps
the immune system attacking cancer
cells, a good thing. Then they
classified people as responders or
non-responders, meaning people who did
not experience cancer progression. So
responders to the antiPD1 therapy or
people who did experience disease
progression, non-responders. Then they
focused in on two groups of bacteria
assessed by fecal matter. So I won't
pronounce them, but here they are. One
is a family of bacteria and the other is
a genus or a subset of related bacteria
in that family. They focused on these
two because other studies have shown
there's a link between these bacteria
and cancer therapy. In addition, these
bacteria are linked to reduced
inflammation under correct
circumstances. So, what happened when
they compared these two bacteria in the
non-responders and the responders? Let's
look. And I promise we'll tie this into
probiotics soon. We have the family and
the genus amount on the vertical axis.
And the higher the box and whisker, the
more of each. The red are the
non-responders and the blue are the
responders. As indicated by the
statistics, p values under 0.05 indicate
a difference. The responders have
greater amounts of these bacteria in the
gut. Okay, a notable difference. But
what does this mean to the grand scheme
of what we're discussing here? Well, the
next step the researchers took was to
quantify probiotic use over the last
month across a groups both combined into
one. responders and non-responders
together. If we look at the progression
of cancer, so indicated as survival
probability, so the higher the better on
the vertical axis, we look at time on
the horizontal axis and we have those
who consume probiotics versus those that
didn't. Those that do seem to do worse
than those who don't consume probiotics,
as in they have greater risk of cancer
progression. An alarming result. But
we're talking about unadjusted
correlations here. And on top of that,
the statistics still indicated no
statistically significant effect. So we
certainly can't rely on these data
alone. So the researchers did something
pretty involved. They took fecal matter
from the cancer patients that were
responsive and transferred it to
germfree mice, meaning these mice don't
have their own gut bacteria. Now these
mice were then exposed to either sterile
water or given one of two probiotics to
consume over several days. Then they
were injected with melanoma tumors. So
in brief, they took mice without their
own gut bacteria and gave them human
bacteria from the people who have better
cancer outcomes. They also injected
these vice with cancer cells after
consuming probiotics or not. This all
allows the researchers to create more of
a cause and effect relationship instead
of just relying on simple correlation.
Here we see what happened by looking at
tumor size across all three groups. The
higher the lines, the greater the tumor
size. So a bad thing as is evident to
you probably those two groups given the
different probiotics were in worse shape
with nearly 10 times increase in tumor
size compared to the control. So these
data further affirm that probiotics have
negative consequences on cancer
progression. Still, there are multiple
nuances that we need to get into. But
before that, let's get into the second
gut health habit and its remarkably
different effects. I suppose it would
also be a good time to mention here that
there's data on what happens to our
immune cells on probiotics. What happens
to our gut diversity and what happens
when you combine gut health nutrients.
I'll be covering that in the extended
version of this video which is available
to the physionic insiders which includes
articles, a library of exclusive videos,
a private podcast, live sessions, and
more. If you're interested, check it out
in the description box. But don't talk
our ears off about the benefits of
probiotics, please. We'd rather discuss
the weather.
Not really. As the study title
indicates, the other gut health nutrient
is dietary fiber. So, not only did the
researchers ask about probiotic
consumption, but they asked the patients
about their dietary fiber intake. They
separated them based on if they were
low- fiber consumers or high-fiber
consumers. And they did the same thing.
Tried to identify the relationship to
cancer progression. This time there was
a clear and statistically identified
link between fiber and cancer
progression. Those that consumed more
had much less cancer progression
compared to those that consumed low or
no fiber. Naturally, they did a similar
experiment that they did with probiotics
with the mice, except these were not
germfree mice. Here, we're again looking
at tumor growth in mice under the same
circumstances, but this time on a low-
fiber or high-fiber diet. In addition,
they're treating the mice with the same
anti-cancer treatment, the antiPD1
therapy. Remarkably, we see that mice on
the low- fiber diet and those mice not
given the treatment experience equally
quick tumor growth. Yet, when the
treatment is paired with fiber, the
tumor does not progress at all. This
suggests that fiber, for a lack of
better word, unlocks the effectiveness
of an anti-cancer therapy. Fair enough.
We now have some distinguishing features
between these two gut health
consumables, but it wouldn't be
responsible to just leave it there
because there are several things that
you should know. For one, while the
combination of associative data in
humans and experimental data in mice
creates a great story, it is solid
evidence, it still needs some work and
we can't necessarily uh jump to cause
and effect. Although it is stronger than
just pure associative evidence. I'd also
mention that the researchers went
through a lot of hoops to reach these
results. They identified responders and
non-responders chose a bacteria family
to focus on. They created their own cut
offs for sufficient and insufficient
fiber. They didn't quantify the amounts
or types of probiotics consumed. And the
experimental design for the fiber mouse
study and the probiotic mouse study had
a few differences in design. So, all
this to say, this seems more exploratory
than dead set proof. I'd like to see
more before condemning all probiotics. I
should also point out, because people
tend to take these kinds of data as
black and white, that probiotics can
still be beneficial in other ways, even
if they're not beneficial in this case.
Not all good things are universally
good. That's where nuance and education
are critical. And the same could be said
of fiber. Even if, as a general rule,
fiber has been noted to have widespread
health benefits, including here. So, if
you have cancer, especially melanoma,
and you are on an anti-cancer therapy,
this study lightly suggests that
probiotics aren't your friend, but
dietary fiber is your friend and can
really help increase the potency of your
anti-cancer treatment. So, you can tell
the yoga podcast listening Mark that
probiotics aren't always the best thing
ever. But you know what is? This next
video. It truly is the best thing ever.
Now, let me bore you to death with why I
think you should watch